<?xml version='1.0'?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
		xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		version="5.0"
		xml:lang="en">
	<title>Balloonist 2.0.3 User Manual</title>
	
	<info>
		<copyright>
			<year>2016</year>
			<holder>Dave Horlick</holder>
		</copyright>
	</info>

	<chapter>
		<title>Getting Started</title>
		
		<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> is a software application to help layout comics
		text balloons and panels.</para>
		
		<section>
			<title>System Requirements</title>
			
			<para>To run <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>, you will need a computer
			equipped with Apple Mac OS X (10.4 or better), Microsoft Windows, Linux,
			or Solaris.</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="getting-started">
			<title>Installation</title>
			
			<section>
				<title>Mac OS X</title>
				<para>The Macintosh version of <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> requires Mac OS X 10.4 (<quote>Tiger</quote>) or better.</para>
				
				<para>You should be presented with a Finder window containing the <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
				application. With some web browsers, you may first need to double-click the
				downloaded archive file, which will have a name like <code>balloonist-2.0.dmg</code>.</para>
				
				<para>Finally, drag the <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> application
				icon to your Applications folder. You should now
				be able to run <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> from your Application folder
				by double-clicking on it. It may take a while to open.</para>
			</section>
			
			<section>
				<title>Windows</title>
				<!-- see http://www.java.com/en/download/help/sysreq.xml for system requirements -->
				
				<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> for Windows comes packaged
				as a zip archive. Windows XP is able to handle zip
				archives natively, but earlier versions
				of Windows may require additional archive management
				software like WinZip
				(<link xl:href="http://www.winzip.com">http://www.winzip.com</link>).</para>
				
				<para>Copy your unpacked <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
				distribution to the <code>Program Files</code> directory
				on your computer using Windows Explorer. This will typically
				be located on your <code>c:</code> drive. You should be able to run
				<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> from here by double-clicking on its
				application icon, which will be labeled <code>Balloonist.exe</code>.</para>
				
				<para>If, after double-clicking, you are presented with a toolbar and
				workspace, then your installation  is complete and you may advance to the
				next section.</para>
				
				<para>If, on the other hand, you receive an alert dialogue,
				you may need to install additional software.
				<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> requires the Java Runtime Environment
				to operate. Should you receive a message
				that Java needs to be installed or "Could not find the main class", dismiss the dialogue and
				obtain an appropriate <link linkend="java">Java Runtime Environment</link>.</para>
			</section>
			
			<section>
				<title>Other Operating Systems</title>
				
				<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> should be able to run on any
				system capable of operating a <link linkend="java">version 1.4 Java Runtime
				Environment</link> or better. Java is installed by default on Solaris, and
				also ships with most Linux distributions.</para>
				
				<para>Download and unzip the Java <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
				distribution to your home directory or a subdirectory underneath it.</para>
				
				<para>Once unpackaged, you should be able to open the resulting
				<code>balloonist.jar</code> file from your desktop manager.</para>

				<para>Some older desktop managers may not have a file association for
				Java executables. Others may incorrectly associate them with a zip
				archive management application. To manually start
				<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>, open up a command shell, change to the
				unpacked directory using the <code>cd</code> command, and enter the
				instruction <code>java -jar balloonist.jar</code></para>
			</section>

			<section xml:id="java">
				<title>Java Runtime Environment Information</title>
				
				<para>Java is a framework for safe and portable software
				applications. Under most circumstances, you shouldn't need
				to know or care that it's being used.</para>
				
				<para>At release time, 
				<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> worked with versions 1.4, 5.0, 6.0, 7.0 and 8.0
				of the Java Runtime Environment. Some features are available
				only under version 6.0 or better.</para>
				
				<para>Java can be obtained at
				<link xl:href="http://www.java.com/">http://www.java.com/</link></para>
				
				<para xml:id="default-java">To set a particular Runtime Environment as the
				default for OS X, open the utility installed at
				<code>/Applications/Utilities/Java/(Java version folder)/Java Preferences</code>
				and drag that Runtime first in the preferred Java Application Runtime
				list. If no such utility exists, you may need to run
				Software Update, which is available under the Apple Menu.</para>
			</section>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			
			<title>Help</title>
			
			<para>This documentation is available at any time from within the Balloonist Help item
			under the application's Help Menu.</para>
			
		</section>
		
	</chapter>
	<chapter xml:id="meat">
		<title>Using Balloonist</title>

		<section>
			<title>Workspace Geography</title>

			<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> presents documents in an
			integrated workspace. The central Artwork Pane
			of this workspace depicts your artwork.
			It can be edited with items selected from the
			pull-down menus, or with the vertical toolbar
			along the left-hand side of the screen.</para>
			
			<figure>
				<title>The workspace</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="workspace.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
						
			<para>A Properties Pane in the upper right-hand
			corner of the Workspace provides more detailed
			control over artwork characteristics.</para>

			<para>When first started, <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
			provides a default panel layout. This can be
			<link linkend="layout">changed</link> from the Properties
			Pane, or new layouts can be generated from templates under
			the New sub menu in the File menu.</para>

			<para>The Object Hierarchy Pane provides a view of your artwork
			broken up into a component tree. This tree should allow you
			to easily select portions of your artwork, even if obscured or too
			thin to easily click on.</para>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Properties Pane</title>
			
			<para>Artwork properties can be edited from the
			Properties Pane, located in the upper right-hand section of the Workspace.</para>
			
			<para>Fields are linked to the location and dimensions of
			selected elements. A units dropdown control allows these dimensions
			to be viewed and edited using different systems of measurement.</para>
			
			<para>If an artwork element is contained by a <link linkend="panels">panel</link>,
			its position coordinates will be specified relative reference frame of that panel.</para>

			<para>If multiple items are selected, the Properties Pane will
			do its best to average their properties.</para>			
						
			<para>Although <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> allows artwork
			elements to be positioned to a very specific number
			of decimal places, we suggest you refrain from doing so.
			Instead, concentrate on aligning your artwork elements to make them look best.</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="layout">
			<title>Layout</title>
			
			<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>'s Layout Properties Pane
			can help simplify the task of panel layout by automatically adjusting
			several panels at once.</para>
			
			<para>The Properties Pane becomes available when no artwork
			elements are selected. If there is an active selection
			and you would like to release it, choose Select None from the
			Edit menu, or choose the Selection tool from the toolbar and
			click outside the drawing area.</para>
			
			<para>Changes to any of the fields in the Layout properties pane
			will typically result in an automatic re-layout of your artwork's panels.
			If you are unhappy with any of the changes, you can always Undo them from
			the Edit Menu.</para>
			
			<para>Automatic Layout may also be turned off from the
			<link linkend="page">Page Properties Pane</link>.</para>
			
			<para>The layout itself is depicted in the artwork pane as a
			light gray rectangle behind the panels, with a gray outline.
			The margin fields control whitespace located between the layout
			and the edge of the page.</para>
			
			<para>The layout's width and height are determined by the
			<link linkend="page">page dimensions</link> and the layout's margins.</para>
			
			<figure>
				<title>Layout in the Artwork and Properties Panes</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="layout.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			
			<para>The number of panels can also be specified. While panel layout is
			set to automatic, picking a number of panels that is
			greater than the existing panel count will result in the implicit addition
			of new panels. If you specify a smaller number, panels will be removed
			backwards in sequence from the end of the list in the Object Hierarchy.
			Again, you can always Undo layout operations, which lets you easily
			recover any panels that have been inadvertently removed.</para>
			
			<para>Other fields set the aspect ratio (or shape) of panels,
			and the default dimensions of the <link linkend="gutters">gutters</link>
			between them. Higher aspect ratios correspond to wider panels.</para>
			
			<para>Since it overrides any changes that have been made to individual
			panels, you will typically want to customize layout early on in your
			artwork's lifetime.</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="page">
			<title>Page</title>
			
			<para>To change the overall dimensions of your artwork, you can select
			the outermost and uppermost node in the Object Hierarchy Pane, titled
			"Page".</para>
			
			<para>In addition to width and height fields, this Property Pane also
			provides radio buttons that can used to deactivate or reactivate
			automatic panel layout.</para>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>The Toolbar</title>

			<para>When you start <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>, the
			Selection Tool is active in the Toolbar. The
			Selection Tool looks like an arrow and allows you
			to select balloons and their sub-components.</para>

			<para>Other more conceptual artwork
			elements, like panels, must be selected
			from the Object Hierarchy Pane.</para>

			<para>The other tools in <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>'s toolbar
			are used to create artwork elements.</para>
			
			<table frame='all'><title>Toolbar Legend</title>
				<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='2' rowsep='2'>
					<colspec colname='icon'/>
					<colspec colname='title'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/word.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Word Balloon</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/word-curved.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Word Balloon with a Curved Stem</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/word-stemless.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Stemless Word Balloon</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/panel.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Panel</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/thought.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Thought Balloon</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/thought-stemless.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Stemless Thought Balloon</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/narration-free.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Narration</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/lollipop.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Lollipop</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/starburst.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Starburst</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="../resources/icons/gouache.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Gouache</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			
			<para>If you use the mouse to
			position the pointer over one of the toolbar buttons, a tool-tip
			will momentarily appear, identifying the associated artwork element.</para>
			
			<section xml:id="zoomer">
				<title>Zoomer</title>
			
				<para>At the bottom of the toolbar, you should see a vertical slider control.
				This is the <emphasis>Zoomer</emphasis>. As you slide the Zoomer up and down,
				the view in the Artwork Pane is scaled without permanently affecting your
				artwork. A percentage beneath the slider indicates the selected display
				magnification.</para>

				<para>You can always return to a 1:1 scale by choosing the Actual Size
				command from the View Menu.</para>
			</section>
				
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Artwork Elements</title>
			
			<section>
				
				<title>Balloons</title>
				
				<para><emphasis>Balloons</emphasis> are a common dialogue 
				element in comics. They typically consist of text circumscribed
				by an outline. This dialogue may be spoken or
				unspoken.</para>

				<para><emphasis>Stems</emphasis> refer to pointers
				emanating from balloon perimeters. Stems attribute
				dialogue to one or more characters. Some people use
				the term "tails" to describe this feature.</para>

				<para>Balloon outlines often consist of ovals.
				The character of these ovals vary widely, a fact
				which has complicated the use of software
				in their generation.</para>

				<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> tries to reproduce
				as much of this diversity as possible by allowing
				users to <link linkend="shape-props">alter</link> the
				<emphasis>rectangularness</emphasis> of these ovals.</para>
				
				<para>Comics generally distinguish <emphasis>Thought</emphasis>
				Balloons from <emphasis>Speech</emphasis> balloons with round
				<emphasis>ruffles</emphasis> and <emphasis>bubbled</emphasis>
				stems. <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> follows these conventions
				when initially creating artwork elements, but allows you to change
				them afterwards.</para>
				
				<para><emphasis>Starbursts</emphasis> exhibit a jagged style
				of ruffling.</para>
				
				<para>Some comics feature an unbordered style of word balloon attributed
				by a simple straight line. <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> calls these
				balloons <emphasis>Lollipops</emphasis>.</para>
					
				<para><emphasis>Narrations</emphasis> are parallelogram-shaped
				balloons used to describe events or place them in context.</para>
				
				<para><emphasis>Gouache</emphasis> can be used to replace the text in
				balloons from scanned art. Applying gouache results in a lettered and unbordered
				white oval. This may be useful for language translation, scanlation, or perhaps those
				replace-the-dialogue contests in the newspaper and certain curmudgeonly blogs.</para>
				
				<para>New artwork elements, balloons included, are automatically
				<link linkend="selections">selected</link> upon creation. The unstemmed portion of
				a balloon that has been selected will appear nestled within a translucent blue rectangle.</para>
				
				<section>
					
					<title>Balloon Properties</title>
					
					<para>When a balloon is selected, the Properties Pane displays a number
					of specialized controls for its configuration.</para>
					
					<figure>
						<title>Balloon properties</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="balloon-props.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
		
					<para xml:id="color-chart-tool">A color chart tool allows you to change the colors of the
					outline and interior of some selected elements. Color chart tools depict
					a filled arc. To change the balloon's interior color, click and
					pull-down the filled portion of the arc. The change the balloon's
					outline color, click and pull-down the outline portion of the arc.</para>
		
					<figure>
						<title>A color chart tool</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="color-chart-tool.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					
					<para>You may also change the thickness of a balloon's outline.
					Unlike other properties, outline thickness is always measured in points,
					and may not exceed 5.0.</para>

				</section>
				
				<section xml:id="balloon-text">
					
					<title>Balloon Text</title>

					<para>Text for selected balloons can be edited and styled
					in the Properties Pane's text area, which can be found at its bottom.
					To add or revise balloon text, click the mouse at the desired location
					and start typing or entering text using another input method. Text can be selected,
					copied, cut, and pasted from the text area in the same manner as in other
					applications.</para>
					
					<para>Dropdown boxes in the Properties Pane allow you to change the
					font family and size of selected text. Certain fonts will 
					<link linkend="uneditably-pasteable-fonts">be replaced</link> if
					pasted into other software applications or exported to PDF format.
					The names of these fonts are italicized and colored in the font family dropdown
					control. For best results, stick with fonts whose names are not
					italicized.</para>
					
					<para>The default font for new balloon text can be configured using the
					<link linkend="prefs">Preferences</link> command.</para>
					
					<para>The Format pull-down menu can be used to provide boldfacing, italics,
					or underlining. It can also be used to remove these attributes.</para>
					
					<para>You can override the natural layout of text within your balloons
					by inserting newlines into them. To do this, click on the desired location
					in the text area and then press the Return key.</para>
					
					<para>The Vertical checkbox can be used to orient
					text from top-to-bottom and right-to-left. This is most useful
					for Chinese and Japanese writing, but can be used with text
					in any language.</para>
					
					<para>Text is offset from the exterior of its balloon by configurable
					margins. When a balloon is selected, the Artwork Pane illustrates this
					using a <emphasis>balloon yolk</emphasis>. Balloon yolks are indicated by
					a dashed, red oval.</para>
					
					<figure>
							<title>A balloon yolk</title>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="yolk.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</figure>
					
					<para>To break balloon text across several sections when there is more
					than one shape, use the tab key. You can consolidate shapes within a
					balloon using the <link linkend="merge">Merge command</link>, or the
					<link linkend="rearrange-shapes">Object Hierarchy</link>.</para>
				
				</section>
				
				<section>
					
					<title>Shapes</title>
					
					<para>Clicking a balloon's disclosure triangle or plus sign in the Object
						Hierarchy will usually reveal that it is a container for one or more shapes.
						These shapes can be selected by clicking on their names in the Object
						Hierarchy.</para>
						
					<para xml:id='shape-props'>Attributes of selected shapes can be adjusted
					using the Properties Pane. These attributes can include background color,
					outline color, rectangularness, location, dimensions, and name.</para>

					<figure>
						<title>A rectangularness slider</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="rectangularness-slider.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>


					<para xml:id="rearrange-shapes">Shapes can be re-arranged by dragging
					them to a new location
					in the Object Hierarchy. Shapes can be relocated within and amongst
					balloons. They may not be moved outside balloons.</para>
						
					<para>The height and preferred width of any balloon <emphasis>ruffles</emphasis>
					(or prongs) can be changed
					from the Ruffles tab in a selected balloon's Properties Pane.</para>

					<figure>
						<title>The Ruffles Property Pane</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="ruffles.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>

					<para>The plus button at the bottom of the pane can add up to ten ruffle harmonics.
					To delete a ruffle harmonic, click on its number in the list to hilight it, and then
					press the minus button.</para>

					<para>Another dropdown control, at the rightmost portion of the pane's bottom,
					allow the ruffle type to be varied from <emphasis>round</emphasis> to
					<emphasis>jagged</emphasis>.</para>

					<para>Thought balloons and starbursts have ruffles by default.
					Ruffles may also be added to other balloon ovals.</para>						
					
				</section>
				
				<section>

					<title>Stems</title>
					
					<para>Clicking on a shape's disclosure triangle or plus sign in the Object
						Hierarchy will
						reveal any contained attribution stems. Stems are characterized by a
						<emphasis>root</emphasis>, which is the part where the balloon and the
						stem touch, and a
						<emphasis>focus</emphasis>, which is the most distant point on the stem
						and generally also the thinnest.
						<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> sometimes refers to the
						<emphasis>leading edge</emphasis> of a stem. This is the first point on
						the stem's root that is encountered when tracing around a clock face,
						clock-wise, from 3 o'clock.</para>

					<para>The Properties Pane can be used to adjust the focal points, root, width,
					style, and curvature of selected stems.</para>						
						
					<figure>
						<title>Stem properties</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="stem-properties.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					
					<para><emphasis>Balloons</emphasis> supports three types of stems:
					<emphasis>icicle</emphasis>, <emphasis>bubbled</emphasis>, and
					<emphasis>lollipop</emphasis>. When a selected stem is bubbled, the
					user is presented with an additional slider in the type options area of the
					Stem properties pane. This slider can control the <emphasis>density</emphasis>
					of the bubbles.</para>
						
					<para xml:id="stem-curvature">Starting with version 2.0, <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> can
					<emphasis>curve</emphasis> stems. The easiest way to produce a curved
					stem is by using the <emphasis>Word Balloon with a Curved Stem tool</emphasis>
					in the toolbar.</para>
					
					<para>Fine control over stem curvature can be achieved using three
					sliders in the bottom righthand portion of the Stem properties pane.
					The top two of these sliders control the <emphasis>inclination</emphasis>
					at the root and focus of the stem. When a stem is selected, manipulating the
					inclination sliders will rotate special tangent lines in the artwork
					pane. The stem's curve will follow those tangent lines at each end.</para>
					
					<figure>
						<title>A Curved Stem</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="curved-stem.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					
					<para>The inclination sliders are also useful for jimmying around the
					bubbles in a bubbled stem.</para>
					
					<para>When starting from an uncurved stem, you will need to adjust
					<emphasis>both</emphasis> inclination sliders before you will notice any
					curvature.</para>
					
					<para>The <emphasis>rigidity</emphasis> slider lets you flatten a curved
					stem.</para>
					
					<figure>
						<title>A Curved and Flattened Stem</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="curved-flattened-stem.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					
					<para>The toolbar offers most balloons in stemmed and unstemmed varieties.
						Additionally, stems can usually be added later using the Item Menu.</para>
	
					<para>Like shapes, stems can also be rearranged using the
						Object Hierarchy Pane.</para>
				</section>	
				
				<section xml:id="merge">

					<title>Merge &amp; Part</title>

					<para>The Merge command under the Arrange Menu can be used to merge
					the shapes from several balloons into one. This operation can be
					reversed with the Part command.</para>

					<para>After clicking in the text area, you can use the tab key
					to break text across sections in a merged balloon.</para>

					<figure>
						<title>Merged Thought Balloons</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="merge.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>

					<para>Upon merging, the newly-composed balloons sections are
					implicitly ordered spatially, so that text flows as appropriate to
					its vertical or horizontal orientation. This operation can also be performed
					later from the Arrange Menu, should subsequent relocations upset
					proper flow. Text flow amongst sections can also be established manually,
					by dragging and dropping shapes in a balloon's node in the Object Hierarchy.</para>

					<para>To tie two merged balloons together, simply add a stem to one and drag
					that stem's focus into the body of the other.</para>

					<figure>
						<title>Tied Word Balloon Ovals</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="tied.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>

					<para>You can also use merging to <emphasis>skewer</emphasis> an oval
					on another oval's stem.</para>

					<figure>
						<title>A Skewered Balloon Oval</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="skewered.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>

				</section>
				
			</section>
			
			<section xml:id="panels">

				<title>Panels</title>

				<para>The artwork elements described so far can be placed inside
				<emphasis>panels</emphasis>. Panels are generally rectangular shapes
				that comics use to group together coincident events.</para>

				<para>Panels <emphasis>clip</emphasis> contained artwork elements.
				This means that any portion of a contained artwork element will be
				hidden from view, as if it were in matted picture frame.</para>
				
				<figure>
					<title>A Balloon Clipped by a Panel</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="clipped.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				
				<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> will attempt to arrange text
				in clipped balloons so that it is <emphasis>not</emphasis> clipped,
				and so that it doesn't overlap its panel's inner margin. When a panel is
				selected, its inner margin can be configured from the Properties Pane.</para>

				<para>If you want an artwork element to appear as though it's inside a 
				particular panel, but you don't want the artwork element to be clipped,
				you may place the artwork element inside the outermost, <emphasis>page</emphasis>
				element, and position then it over the desired panel.</para>

				<para>Newly-created <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> documents
				have a default arrangement of panels. The particulars of this
				arrangement will vary depending on the kind of <emphasis>stationery</emphasis>
				used to create the document. Stationery is available under the
				File Menu's New submenu.</para>

				<para>When no elements are selected
				in the Artwork Pane, the Properties Pane allows the default
				panel arrangement to be <link linkend="layout">quickly reconfigured</link>.</para>

				<para>To avoid complicating the selection of balloons and images, panels
				cannot be selected from the Artwork Pane. Instead, they must be selected from the
				Object Hierarchy Pane. The Properties Pane can be used to reshape
				selected panels, or to alter their inner margins. Selected panels
				may also be resized by clicking and dragging their corners and sides
				in the Artwork Pane.</para>
				
				<para>If an artwork element is contained by a panel, its coordinates are
				specified relative to that panel.</para>
				
				<section xml:id="gutters">
				
					<title>Gutters</title>
					
					<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> implicitly recognizes the
					interstitial space between panels as <emphasis>Gutters</emphasis>.
					Gutters are depicted with a pattern resembling the dimpled
					surface of toy blocks.</para>
					
					<figure>
						<title>Gutters</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="gutter.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					
					<para>Gutters can be easily moved around by pressing the mouse and dragging
					on them. They do not need to be selected first.</para>
					
					<para>Panels on either
					side of a re-located gutter will be resized to accommodate its
					new placement.</para>
				
				</section>
				
			</section>

			<section>

				<title>Crowds</title>

				<para>A <emphasis>Crowd</emphasis> is a special container used to
				group together balloons so that their text will remain aligned
				relative to each other. <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> will
				prevent the text inside crowded balloons from overlapping.</para>

				<para>Crowds cannot be created directly. Whenever a balloon is
				created inside a panel,
				<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> will implicitly create a
				<emphasis>Crowd</emphasis> for the new balloon, if one is not
				already present.</para>

				<para>If you would prefer a balloon to obscure the text in its
				overlapped counterparts, you
				can move it outside its crowd by dragging and dropping it in the
				Object Hierarchy Pane, or by cutting and pasting.</para>

				<para>Crowded balloons will respect each other's margin settings.
				Margins of selected balloon can be changed using the Properties
				Pane.</para>

			</section>
			
			<section xml:id="images">
				
				<title>Images</title>
				
				<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> allows you to add image content
				to your artwork via the Place commands under the File Menu. Placed
				images can be linked or embedded.</para>
				
				<para>By default, only files with an extension identifying them as JPG,
				PNG, or GIF content will be selectable in resulting file dialog. To override this
				behavior, hold down the option key (Mac OS X) or alt key (other operating
				systems) when you activate the desired menu item.</para>
				
				<para>When you save your artwork, <emphasis>Linked</emphasis> images will
				be stored as Uniform Resource Locator (URL) addresses. These should be familiar
				from web browsers, and can be expressed using a variety of protocols. These
				protocols include <code>http</code> and <code>ftp</code> for images on the
				World Wide Web, and <code>file</code> for images on your local file system.</para>
				
				<para>When you change a URL address, or re-open a saved document, linked image
				URL's will be consulted to obtain image content.</para>
				
				<para><emphasis>Embedded</emphasis> images are actually saved, pixel for
				pixel, with your artwork. Embedded images also feature a URL address, but
				it is only provided for reference.</para>
				
				<para>The Properties Pane can change the URL address of selected images.
				It also permits you to toggle them between linked and embedded states. Be warned
				that changing an image from embedded to linked will cause any cached image
				content to be lost.</para>
				
				<para>If nothing is selected, a placed image will be dropped onto the page,
				behind any panels. If a panel is selected, <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
				will place the image inside that panel. If an artwork element is selected,
				the image will be placed inside the same panel that contains that element.</para>
				
				<para>When resizing an image by dragging one of its corners, you can maintain
				the image's aspect ratio by holding down the shift key.</para>
				
				<para>If an images becomes sheared and you'd like to restore its original
				aspect ratio, use the Reset Width or Reset Height button in the Properties
				Pane.</para>
			</section>
			
			<section xml:id="selections">

				<title>Selections</title>

				<para>Artwork elements are automatically
				<emphasis>selected</emphasis> upon creation.</para>

				<para>Artwork elements can be <emphasis>deselected</emphasis>
				by clicking within an empty region of the document, or by choosing the
				<emphasis>Select None</emphasis> item from the Edit Menu.</para>

				<para>To select an element that is not currently selected, use the mouse to move
				the cursor over that element, and click once.</para>

				<para>Alternately, elements may be selected by clicking on their names in the
				Object Hierarchy Pane.</para>
				
				<para>To select multiple elements, you may use the Shift key in combination with
				the methods above. If nothing is selected, you may also select multiple elements
				by pressing the mouse and dragging a selection rectangle around elements in the
				Artwork Pane.</para>
				
				<section>

					<title>Moving &amp; Resizing Selections</title>
				
					<para>Selected elements can be relocated by positioning the mouse cursor over them,
					pressing the mouse button, and dragging the mouse to a new location. This motion can
					be constrained to a particular axis by holding down the Shift key.</para>
					
					<para>Most selected elements can be resized by dragging their sides and corners
					in the Artwork Pane. The cursor's appearance will change when positioned over these
					spots of a selected element. Resizing can also be constrained using the Shift key.</para>
	
					<para>Properties of selected elements can be changed using the
					Properties Pane.</para>
				
				</section>
				
				<section>

					<title>Moving Stem Components</title>
					
					<para>Components of selected stems (or the stems of selected balloons) can also be
					relocated from the Artwork Pane. The mouse cursor will change its appearance to indicate
					when it is positioned over a stem or its focus.</para>
					
					<para>When you move a balloon, the focal points that its stems point to ordinarily
					remain fixed. To move stem focal points along with their balloon, hold down the Command key
					when using Mac OS X, then press and drag as before. On other platforms, use the second
					mouse button to re-locate a balloon and its stems together.</para>
					
					<para>To resize a stem root, select its stem and use the root width slider in the
					Properties Pane.</para>

				</section>

			</section>
			
		</section>	
		
		<section>
			<title>Object Hierarchy Pane</title>
			
			<para>The Object Hierarchy Pane presents a tree view of your artwork elements.
			Containers are represented by folder icons. These can be opened to reveal
			contents by clicking the accompanying disclosure triangle (Mac OS X) or
			plus sign.</para>
			
			<para>Artwork elements may be selected by clicking on their companion
			icons or names in the Object Hierarchy Pane. Similarly, selections made in
			the Artwork Pane should also be reflected here.</para>
			
			<para>Artwork elements can be clicked, dragged, and relocated within the
			Object Hierarchy Pane, with some restrictions. A shape can only be located
			within a balloon, and a stem can only be located inside a shape.</para>
		</section>

		<section>

			<title>Leftovers</title>

			<para>Artwork elements can also be reorganized using the commands under the Arrange
			Menu. Bring Forward, Send Backward, Bring to Front, and Send to Back each affect
			which portions appear "on top" when artwork elements overlap. This is sometimes
			referred to as z-order. Properly expanded, the Object Hierarchy represents
			the sequence of artwork elements.</para>

			<para>Most operations in <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> can be undone and redone
			using the items under the Edit Menu.</para>

			<para>In addition to the <link linkend="zoomer">zoomer</link>, the View Menu can also be
			used to change the magnification level of the Artwork Pane.</para>
			
			<para>If the view is scaled such that your units of choice would appear reasonably
			large, you can reveal rulers by resizing the application window to larger than
			your artwork.</para>
			
			<para>When you are done using <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>, you can end your session
			using the Quit command. On Mac OS X, Quit is located under the Application Menu.
			On other platforms, it can be found under the File menu.</para>
		</section>
		
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		
		<title>Document Management</title>
		
		<para>The File Menu provides commands to generate new artwork using the default
		layout, from stationery, or with a single panel displaying an existing image file.
		The commands to start from existing images work like their counterpart commands
		to <link linkend="images">place images</link>.</para>
		
		<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> artwork can be opened and saved using
		items under the File Menu. All artwork elements, including text, balloons, and
		<link linkend="images">any embedded image content</link>, will be saved with
		your document.</para>
		
		<para>New documents will default to the file extension <code>bna</code>.
		We recommend keeping this file extension, since some platforms
		require it to associate documents with <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>.</para>
		
		<para>You may save a copy of a document using a new name with the Save As
		command under the File Menu.</para>
		
		<para>Fonts are not embedded within <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
		documents. You will receive a warning upon opening any document that uses
		fonts that are not available on your system. References to unavailable fonts will be
		implicitly mapped to the default font as set in your <link linkend="prefs">user
		preferences</link>.
		If you save a file after font references have been replaced, the old font references
		will be lost.</para>
		
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		
		<!--
		<info>
			<keywordset>
				<keyword>distribute</keyword>
				<keyword>distribution</keyword>
			</keywordset>
		</info>
		-->
	
		<title>Interacting with the Outside World</title>
		
		<para>There wouldn't be much point to producing artwork in
		<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> if you couldn't share that artwork with the outside
		world. Consequently, <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> can print your artwork,
		export it to a number of standard file formats, and copy and paste portions
		of it to familiar graphics software applications.</para>
		
		<indexterm><primary>distribution</primary></indexterm>
		<indexterm><primary>distribute</primary></indexterm>
		
		<section>
			
			<title>Printing</title>
			
			<para>Artwork can be printed by choosing the Print item under
			the File Menu. If your artwork is taller than it is wide, it will
			be printed using portrait orientation. If your artwork is wider than
			it is tall, it will be printed using landscape orientation.</para>
			
			<para>Alternately, artwork can be <link linkend="pdf-export">exported</link>
			to another
			graphics software application, such as Adobe
			Reader, and printed there. This can be helpful if your printer
			can't handle the size of your artwork, and you would like to
			scale the printed image to fit on a single physical page.</para>
			
			<para xml:id="fractional-print-nudge">When printing directly from the software on Mac OS X,
			<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
			will nudge panels that are positioned at fractional point coordinates to whole number
			coordinates. This corresponds to a distance smaller than 0.353 millimeters, and is
			not generally noticeable. Nevertheless, if you'd prefer to avoid the limitation, you
			can print from another application after Exporting As PDF from the File Menu.</para>
			
		</section>
	
		<section>
			
			<title>File Exchange</title>
			
			<para>Using the Export item under the File Menu, <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
			lets you to write your artwork to PDF, SVG 1.0, or SVG 1.2 vector formats. You
			may also generate PNG images.</para>
			
			<section>

				<title>Vector Export Formats</title>
			
				<para xml:id="pdf-export">Adobe Portable Document Format
				(<link xl:href="http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/adobepdf.html">PDF</link>)
				is an established industry standard
				that is well supported by print shops and publishers.</para>
				
				<para xml:id="svg-export">Scalable Vector Graphics
				(<link xl:href="http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/">SVG</link>) is a newer, more open
				standard. SVG 1.0 is
				already in widespread use. SVG 1.2 has not yet been fully defined, but will feature
				more sophisticated support for wrapped text. <emphasis>Balloonist's</emphasis> support
				for SVG 1.2 should be considered experimental.</para>
				
				<para>SVG can be used by many graphics software applications, including
				<link xl:href="http://www.adobe.com/products/illustrator">Adobe Illustrator</link>
				and <link xl:href="http://www.inkscape.org">Inkscape</link>. SVG support is also being built
				into <link xl:href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/svg/">next-generation web browsers</link>.</para>
				
				<para>SVG handles fonts less rigidly than PDF does, which can be useful
				for working locally with <link linkend="uneditably-pasteable-fonts">certain fonts</link>.</para>
				
				<para>Mac OS X users may also generate PDF files from the dialog box reached
				from the Print command. This option is affected by the
				<link linkend="fractional-print-nudge">whole number panel coordinate restriction</link>
				that also affects printing directly from the software on Mac OS X.</para>
			
			</section>
			
			<section>
				<title>Image Export</title>
				
				<para>Other export options allow you to generate image files. All <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
				deployments offer output in Portable Network Graphics (PNG)
				images. <link xl:href="http://www.w3.org/Graphics/PNG/">PNG</link> is a handy, compact
				image format supported by most modern web browsers.</para>
				
				<para>If you have <link linkend="java6">Java 6.0</link> or better installed, you can also export images in
				Graphics Interchange Format (GIF).</para>			
			</section>
			
			<section>
				<title>ComicsML Import</title>
			
				<para><emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> also includes basic support for importing
				comics represented in <link xl:href="http://www.jmac.org/projects/comics_ml/">ComicsML</link>
				definition language. This support is available from
				the File Menu.</para>
				
			</section>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			
			<title>Copy and Paste</title>
			
			<para>Once selected, portions of <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> artwork
			can be copied and pasted to any graphics software application with clipboard PDF
			support. These include
			<link xl:href="http://www.adobe.com/products/illustrator">Adobe Illustrator</link>
			and <link xl:href="http://www.corel.com">CorelDRAW</link>.</para>
			
			<para>Unadorned text copied from <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> without its
			parent balloon can be pasted into most software applications.</para>
			
			<para xml:id="editability">On <link linkend="leopard-editability">most platforms</link>, text located inside balloons can be pasted to other applications
			and exported to <link linkend="pdf-export">PDF format</link>
			in a manner that will allow it to be edited later.
			This flexibility may come at the
			expense of rendering accuracy if the destination application does not support
			the same fonts and text characteristics that <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis>
			does.</para>
			
			<para>On platforms where this functionality is available, it is the default behavior. The <link linkend="prefs">Preferences command</link>
			allows you to request that <emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> instead work to
			preserve the accuracy of pasted text at the expense of its
			editability. This option causes text too be pasted and exported to
			PDF format as vector glyphs.</para>
			
			<para xml:id="uneditably-pasteable-fonts">Certain fonts will usually be
			replaced when pasted into another application or exported to PDF.
			Fonts with this restriction are italicized and colored in the font
			family dropdown control. On Mac OS X, these include fonts
			stored in suitcase files, which typically have no file extension and a file
			type code of "FFIL".</para>
			
			<para>Often, this limitation can be overcome by exporting artwork to
			<link linkend="svg-export">SVG format</link>.</para>
			
		</section>
		
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="prefs">
		<title>Preferences</title>
		
		<para>On Mac OS X, the Preferences command can be found under the
		<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> Application Menu. On other platforms,
		it is located under the Help Menu.</para>
		
		<para>The Preferences command brings up a Preferences Window. This
		Window is sub-divided into <emphasis>Text</emphasis>
		and <emphasis>Shape</emphasis> tabs. As you change various
		defaults, you can see their effect on a sample balloon.</para>
		
		<section>
			<title>Text Tab</title>
		
			<para>The Text Tab lets you change the default font
			for <link linkend="balloon-text">balloon text</link>.
			To revert back to the shipping default font, click the Reset button.</para>

			<para>The Text Tab also provides control over the
			<link linkend="editability">transmission of text to other software applications</link>
			through a Preserve dropdown.</para>

			<para>This dropdown affects Copy and Paste, as well as the Export
			As PDF command under the File Menu. It has no effect on the Mac OS X Print Dialog's Save as PDF
			feature, Adobe Acrobat Distiller, or any other external method for PDF Export.</para>
			
			<para>Users running <link linkend="java6">Java 6</link>
			will also be provided with an option to
			<emphasis>kern</emphasis> text. Kerning employs special information stored
			within a font to adjust the horizontal spacing of particular character pairs
			(for example, "A" and "V" or "T" and "o") to use space optimally.</para>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Shape Tab</title>
			
			<para>The Shape Tab establishes default characteristics for the shape and outline
			of balloons. Sliders control default rectangularness,
			<link linkend="color-chart-tool">color</link>,
			text margin, and line thickness.</para>
		</section>
		
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		
		<title>Terms, Conditions, and Licensing</title>
		
		<section xml:id="terms-and-conditions">
			
			<!-- Note: the above id is used to tag this section for inclusion in a 
			software dialog box. Please do NOT change this attribute! -->
			
			<title>Terms &amp; Conditions</title>
			
			<section>
				<title>Usage Agreement</title>

				<para>The authors are not responsible
				for any damages resulting from the use or misuse of this software.
				<emphasis>Balloonist</emphasis> is offered without warranty under a GNU GPL v2 license.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="support">
		
		<title>Known Issues</title>

		<section>
		
			<title>Known Issues</title>
			
			<section>
				<title>Problems with Mixed Arabic and Roman Text on Mac OS X</title>
			
				<para>There is a problem on Max OS X that results in the incorrect layout of
				balloons that mix Arabic and Roman text. Because Mac OS X will implicitly substitute
				characters missing from one font with characters from another, this may also result
				in problems when entering only Roman characters using an Arabic font, or vice versa.</para>
			</section>
			
			<section>
				<title>Placed Image Artifacts on Mac OS X 10.4</title>
				
				<para>Users of Mac OS X 10.4 may experience unwanted tiny, white rectangles in regions of placed images. This problem can be resolved by changing the default Java implementation to Java 2 Standard Edition 5.0 (also sometimes known, confusingly, as "Java Runtime Environment 1.5") or better. This is the default Java version as of Mac OS X 10.5 (Leopard.)</para>

				<para>Apple provides a <link linkend="default-java">utility</link> to set Java 5.0 or better as the default.</para>
			</section>
						
			<section xml:id="leopard-editability">
				<title>Can't Export Text Editably on Mac OS X 10.5</title>
				
				<para>Unfortunately, text cannot be editably exported to PDF, or editably copied-and-pasted to other applications, on Mac OS X 10.5 (Leopard). Instead, text will instead appear as uneditable vector glyphs at the destination. To workaround, export artwork to SVG, instead.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		
	</chapter>
	
</book>

